A Guide to the Jordan Family Collection, 1752-1992 (bulk 1830-1930)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Jordan Family Collection, 1752-1992 (bulk 1830-1930)
The Library of Virginia
42492
28 cu. ft., 69 volumes, and 2 reels of microfilm (Misc. Reel 5399-5400).
Martha Foster
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Martha Foster, Bon Air, Virginia 23235
Biographical Information
Samuel Francis Jordan was born on 9 January 1805. He was the son of Col. John Jordan and Lucy Winn of Rockbridge County, Virginia. He married 1) Hannah Weaver Davis and 2) Elizabeth Leibert Keen. Samuel F. Jordan was engaged in the production of iron, and owned furnaces in Allegany, Amherst, Bath, Botetourt, Louisa, and Rockbridge Counties. He died on 8 June 1872. His son, Charles Francis Jordan, was born at the Bath Iron Works in Goshen, Virginia on 8 July 1837. He worked with his father in various family-owned furnaces, before being commissioned a captain in the 1st Virginia Cavalry during the Civil War. He was one of the founders of the town of Buena Vista, and served in the Virginia House of Delegates. Jordan married Mary Ella Hamilton on 24 February 1864. He died in Roanoke, Virginia on 12 May 1922, and is buried in the Stonewall Jackson Cemetery in Lexington. His son, Charles Francis Jordan, Jr. was born on 22 May 1866. He married Amelia Waesche.
Scope and Content
Collection, 1752-1992, of business records and personal papers of the Jordan family of Buena Vista and Lexington, and Rockbridge County, Virginia. The bulk of the collection spans the years 1830-1930, and documents the business activities of Samuel Francis Jordan (1805-1872), and his son Charles Francis Jordan (1837-1922), and the family's iron manufacturing enterprises, and saddle and harness making business. Includes correspondence, accounts and receipts, subject files, ledgers and account books, Joseph Gilmore Papers, oversize items, and ephemera.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1830-1946., Extent: 28 boxes. (Box 1-28)
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Subseries I: Iron Manufacturing, 1830-1889., 7 boxes (3.15 cu. ft.)
    The iron manufacturing correspondence relates to Samuel F. Jordan's ownership in the Bath Iron Works as a partner in Jordan, Davis and Company, later Jordan and Davis, and his subsequent operation of the Buena Vista Furnace after 1848 with his brother Benjamin J. Jordan (1819-1889). Benjamin sold his interest to Samuel in 1852, and the latter continued to operate the Buena Vista property with his sons William Henry Jordan (1829-1886), John Thomas Jordan (1834-1893), and Charles Francis Jordan (1837-1922).
    Topics covered in the letters relate to iron shipments and sales to various commission merchants, including Lewis Webb and Company and Crenshaw and Company of Richmond, and Miller and Roberts and McCorkle and McDaniel of Lynchburg, and to the settlement of outstanding accounts, shipment, storage and sales of iron produced at the Jordan furnaces. There is also a large amount of correspondence concerning the hiring of slaves to work at the various furnaces, and inquiries from slave owners regarding the hired hands' health, employment status, management, treatment, and welfare. There are also letters dealing with the subject of runaways.
    There are also letters written to Jordan from his sons Charles and John while they were serving in the 1st Virginia Cavalry during the Civil War at Harper's Ferry, Charles City County, Fairfax Station, and Brandy Station. There is a description of the unit's participation at the First Battle of Bull Run. Other Civil War correspondence details Jordan's contract to supply pig iron to the Confederate government. There is a large group of letters between Jordan and the Nitre and Mining Bureau, as well as other Civil War-related materials contained in the Subject Files.
    Other topics contained in the correspondence concern land, legal, and financial matters. Subjects in the post-Civil War letters include the discussion of rates with various railroad companies, the attempted sale of the Buena Vista Furnace and Amherst Furnace, and additional correspondence with iron commission merchants, most notably Hoffman, Thompson and Co. of Baltimore, that detail the types of iron that are marketable, prices realized, the state of the current market, and future prospects.
    - 1830. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1831. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1832. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1833 (January-March). (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1833 (April-July). (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 1833 (August-December). (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1834. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1835. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1836 (January-March). (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 1836 (April-July). (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 1836 (August-December). (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 1839, 1841. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - 1845. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 1846. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - 1847. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - 1848 (January-April). (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 1848 (May-August). (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - 1848 (September-December). (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - 1849 (January-February). (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1849 (March-June). (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - 1849 (July-September). (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - 1849 (October-December). (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - 1850 (January-June). (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1850 (July-December). (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1851 (January-June). (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - 1851 (July-December). (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 1852 (January-June). (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - 1852 (July-December). (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - 1853 (January-June). (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - 1853 (July-December). (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1854 (January-February). (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - 1854 (March-May). (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - 1854 (June-August). (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - 1854 (September-December). (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - 1855 (January-June). (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1855 (July-December). (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1856. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1857. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1858 (January-March). (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1858 (April-September). (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1858 (October-December). (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1859 (January-June). (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1859 (July-December). (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - 1860 (January-June). (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - 1860 (July-December). (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 1861 (January-June). (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1861 (July-December). (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1862. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1863 (January-March). (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1863 (April-June). (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1863 (July-September). (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1863 (October-December). (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1864 (January-June). (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1864 (July-December). (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1865. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1866 (January-June). (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1866 (July-December). (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1867. (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - 1868 (January-June). (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1868 (July-December). (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1869. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1870. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1871. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1872 (January-March). (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1872 (April). (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1872 (May-June). (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1872 (July-December). (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1873. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1874 (January-May). (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 1874 (June). (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1874 (July-December). (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 1875. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 1876. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1877. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1878. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 1879 (January-August). (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - 1879 (September-December). (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 1880-1882. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 1883 (January-April). (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1883 (May-June). (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 1883 (July-December). (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 1884 (January-February). (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 1884 (March-April). (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 1884 (May-June). (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - 1884 (July-August). (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - 1884 (September-December). (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - 1885 (January-March). (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1885 (April-June). (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1885 (July-December). (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1886. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1887 (January-July). (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1887 (August-November). (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1887 (December). (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1888. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1889. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Subseries II: Buena Vista Saddle and Harness Company, 1889-1934., 19 boxes ( cu. ft.)
    The earliest letters are addressed to William R. Wilbourn, who served as the company's superintendent, and later secretary and treasurer. He patented the Wilbourn saddle, and later sold the rights to the company. Charles F. Jordan was initially one of five directors, but became president shortly after the company was chartered on 25 May 1889.
    Subjects include letters from potential customers requesting prices and placing orders, as well as existing customers inquiring about the status of the orders they had placed. There are also letters from various other saddle making supply companies and equipment companies. There are employment inquiries, letters from company agents, requests for catalogs, and notices of stockholder and board of directors meetings. There are some copies of outgoing letters, and some of the incoming correspondence has notations as to when they were answered or when a particular order was shipped. There are four letter books containing copies of outgoing letters.
    The Buena Vista Saddle and Harness Company correspondence is arranged in three groups. Most of it is chronological (1889-1934), but there is also a group arranged by month, and thereunder alphabetical by correspondent or company name (1891-1904). Finally, there is a small group arranged alphabetically by correspondent or company name (1892-1900). It is unclear why these different filing systems exist, since the subject matter in all three groups is the same.
    - 1889 (March-September). (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1889 (October-December). (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - 1890 (January). (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - 1890 (February). (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 1890 (March). (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1890 (April). (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1890 (May). (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1890 (June). (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - 1890 (July 1-15). (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 1890 (July 16-31). (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 1890 (August). (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - 1890 (September). (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1890 (October-November). (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - 1890 (December). (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 1891. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - 1892. (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - 1893. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - 1894. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - 1895. (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - 1896. (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - 1897. (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - 1898. (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - 1899. (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - 1900. (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - 1901 (January-March). (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - 1901 (April-May). (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - 1901 (June-August). (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - 1901 (September-December). (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - 1902 (January-March). (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - 1902 (April-June). (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - 1902 (July-September). (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - 1902 (October-December). (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - 1903. (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1903 (January-May). (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - 1903 (June). (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - 1903 (July). (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - 1903 (August). (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - 1903 (September). (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - 1903 (October-December). (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - 1904 (January-March). (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - 1904 (April-May). (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - 1904 (June-July). (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - 1904 (August-September). (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - 1904 (October). (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - 1904 (November-December). (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - 1905 (January-February). (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - 1905 (March). (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - 1905 (April). (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - 1905 (May-June). (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - 1905 (July). (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - 1905 (August). (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - 1905 (September-October). (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - 1905 (November). (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - 1905 (December). (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - 1906 (January 1-15). (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - 1906 (January 16-31). (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - 1906 (February). (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - 1906 (March). (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - 1906 (April). (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - 1906 (May). (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - 1906 (June). (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - 1906 (July). (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - 1906 (August). (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - 1906 (September). (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - 1906 (October-November). (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - 1906 (December). (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - 1907 (January-February). (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - 1907 (March-April). (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - 1907 (May-July). (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - 1907 (August-September). (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - 1907 (October-December). (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - 1908 (January-March). (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - 1908 (April). (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - 1908 (May 1-18). (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - 1908 (May 19-31). (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - 1908 (June-August). (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - 1908 (September-December). (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - 1909 (January-March). (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - 1909 (April-August). (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - 1909 (September). (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - 1909 (October). (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - 1909 (November). (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - 1909 (December). (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - 1910 (January). (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - 1910 (February). (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - 1910 (March). (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - 1910 (April). (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - 1910 (May-December). (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - 1911. (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - 1912. (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - 1913. (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - 1914. (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - 1915. (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - 1916 (January-May). (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - 1916 (June-December). (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - 1917 (January-February). (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - 1917 (March-April). (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - 1917 (May-June). (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - 1917 (July-September). (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - 1917 (October-December). (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - 1918 (January-March). (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - 1918 (April-July). (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - 1918 (August-December). (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - 1919. (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - 1920. (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - 1921. (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - 1922-1927, 1934. (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - January, 1892. (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - January, 1893. (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - January, 1894. (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - January, 1895. (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - January, 1896. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - January, 1898. (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - January, 1899. (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - January, 1900. (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - January, 1901. (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - January, 1902. (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - January, 1903. (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - January, 1904. (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - February, 1892. (Box 16, Folder 13)
    - February, 1893. (Box 16, Folder 14)
    - February, 1894. (Box 16, Folder 15)
    - February, 1895. (Box 16, Folder 16)
    - February, 1896. (Box 16, Folder 17)
    - February, 1897. (Box 16, Folder 18)
    - February, 1898. (Box 16, Folder 19)
    - February, 1899. (Box 16, Folder 20)
    - February, 1900. (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - February, 1901. (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - February, 1902. (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - February, 1903. (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - March, 1892. (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - March, 1893. (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - March, 1894. (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - March, 1895. (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - March, 1896. (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - March, 1897. (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - March, 1898. (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - March, 1899. (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - March, 1900. (Box 17, Folder 12)
    - March, 1901. (Box 17, Folder 13)
    - March, 1902. (Box 17, Folder 14)
    - March, 1903. (Box 17, Folder 15)
    - April, 1892. (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - April, 1893. (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - April, 1894. (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - April, 1895. (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - April, 1896. (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - April, 1897. (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - April, 1898. (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - April, 1899. (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - April, 1900. (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - April, 1902. (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - April, 1903. (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - May, 1892. (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - May, 1893. (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - May, 1894. (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - May, 1895. (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - May, 1896. (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - May, 1897. (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - May, 1898. (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - May, 1899. (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - May, 1900. (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - May, 1901. (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - May, 1902. (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - May, 1903. (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - June, 1892. (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - June, 1893. (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - June, 1894. (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - June, 1895. (Box 19, Folder 12)
    - June, 1896. (Box 19, Folder 13)
    - June, 1897. (Box 19, Folder 14)
    - June, 1898. (Box 19, Folder 15)
    - June, 1899. (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - June, 1900 (A-K). (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - June, 1900 (L-Z). (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - June, 1901. (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - June, 1902. (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - July, 1891. (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - July, 1892. (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - July, 1893. (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - July, 1894. (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - July, 1895. (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - July, 1896. (Box 20, Folder 11)
    - July, 1897. (Box 20, Folder 12)
    - July, 1898. (Box 20, Folder 13)
    - July, 1899. (Box 20, Folder 14)
    - July, 1900. (Box 20, Folder 15)
    - July, 1901. (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - July, 1902. (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - August, 1891. (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - August, 1892. (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - August, 1893. (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - August, 1894. (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - August, 1895. (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - August, 1896. (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - August, 1897. (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - August, 1898. (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - August, 1899. (Box 21, Folder 11)
    - August, 1900. (Box 21, Folder 12)
    - August, 1901. (Box 21, Folder 13)
    - August, 1902. (Box 21, Folder 14)
    - September, 1891. (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - September, 1892. (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - September, 1893. (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - September, 1894. (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - September, 1895. (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - September, 1896. (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - September, 1897. (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - September, 1898. (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - September, 1899. (Box 22, Folder 9)
    - October, 1891. (Box 22, Folder 10)
    - October, 1892. (Box 22, Folder 11)
    - October, 1893. (Box 22, Folder 12)
    - October, 1894. (Box 22, Folder 13)
    - October, 1895. (Box 22, Folder 14)
    - October, 1896. (Box 22, Folder 15)
    - October, 1897. (Box 22, Folder 16)
    - October, 1898. (Box 22, Folder 17)
    - October, 1899. (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - October, 1900. (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - October, 1901. (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - October, 1902. (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - November, 1891. (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - November, 1892. (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - November, 1893. (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - November, 1894. (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - November, 1895. (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - November, 1896. (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - November, 1897. (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - November, 1898. (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - November, 1899. (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - November, 1900. (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - November, 1901. (Box 23, Folder 15)
    - November, 1902. (Box 23, Folder 16)
    - November, 1903. (Box 23, Folder 17)
    - December, 1891. (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - December, 1892. (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - December, 1893. (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - December, 1894. (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - December, 1895. (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - December, 1896. (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - December, 1897. (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - December, 1898. (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - December, 1899. (Box 24, Folder 9)
    - December, 1900. (Box 24, Folder 10)
    - December, 1901. (Box 24, Folder 11)
    - December, 1902. (Box 24, Folder 12)
    - December, 1903. (Box 24, Folder 13)
    - 1892-1900 (A). (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - 1892-1900 (B). (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - 1892-1900 (C). (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - 1892-1900 (D). (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - 1892-1900 (E). (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - 1892-1900 (F). (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - 1892-1900 (G). (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - 1892-1900 (H). (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - 1892-1900 (J). (Box 25, Folder 9)
    - 1892-1900 (K). (Box 25, Folder 10)
    - 1892-1900 (L). (Box 25, Folder 11)
    - 1892-1900 (M). (Box 25, Folder 12)
    - 1892-1900 (Mc). (Box 25, Folder 13)
    - 1892-1900 (N). (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - 1892-1900 (O). (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - 1892-1900 (P). (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - 1892-1900 (R). (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - 1892-1900 (S). (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - 1892-1900 (T). (Box 26, Folder 6)
  - Subseries III: Jordan Manufacturing Company, 1910-1935., 1 box (.45 cu. ft.)
    There is one box of correspondence of the Jordan Manufacturing Company, which was owned and operated by Charles Francis Jordan, Jr. (1866-1956). The company was a manufacturer of door and window frames, moldings, ceilings, siding, and also mission style furniture. Most of the letters concern coal orders and shipments, lumber and building materials, and orders from Jordan for woodworking machinery and parts from various supply companies.
    - 1910. (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - 1911. (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - 1912. (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - 1913 (January-June). (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - 1913 (July-December). (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - 1914 (January-March). (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - 1914 (April-June). (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - 1914 (July-September). (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - 1914 (October-December). (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - 1915 (January-June). (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - 1915 (July-December). (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - 1916. (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - 1917. (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - 1918. (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - 1920-1929. (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - 1930-1935. (Box 27, Folder 16)
  - Subseries IV: Personal Correspondence, 1936-1946., 1 box (.45 cu. ft.)
    There is one box of personal correspondence, containing mainly letters to various family members. The bulk of this group are letters to Mabelle Jordan (1893-1998) from her cousin Beverly Ragland Jordan (1911-1959), while he was serving in the United States Army during World War II, and stationed at Fort Meade, Virginia Beach, New York City, Miami, Camp Atterbury, Indiana, and Cleveland, Ohio.
    - 1936-1939. (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - 1940. (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - 1941. (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - 1942 (January-July). (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - 1942 (August-December). (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - 1943 (January-May). (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - 1943 (June-December). (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - 1944 (January-July). (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - 1944 (August-December). (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - 1945 (January-April). (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - 1945 (May-December). (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - 1946. (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - n.d. (Box 28, Folder 13)
- Series II. Accounts and Receipts, 1829-1941., Extent: 10 boxes. (Box 29-38)
  The accounts and receipts contains both personal and business records, and are arranged by year. There are financial records documenting bar iron sold to customers, freight costs and tolls, lawyers' fees, newspaper subscriptions and advertisements, bonds and notes, land sales, medical expenses, blacksmith fees, general merchandise purchased, such as oats, cornmeal, flour, bacon, butter, beef, and whiskey, timber and livestock, hardware, cloth and linens, clothing, shoes, and sewing expenses, lodging and meals, and tuition and books. There are also satisfied promissory notes included in this series.
  There are receipts for pig iron delivered to the Confederate States iron yard, and the Nitre and Mining Bureau during the Civil War. Also included are accounts and receipts related to the hiring of hands, and the advertising and apprehending of runaway slaves.